<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at St. Paul's Covent-garden on the first Sunday in Lent being the second part of the sermon preached before the Prince of Orange / by Symon Patrick ...</title>
            <author>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56704</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P851</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31758</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12253066</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12253066</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57178</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56704)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57178)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1510:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at St. Paul's Covent-garden on the first Sunday in Lent being the second part of the sermon preached before the Prince of Orange / by Symon Patrick ...</title>
                  <author>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M DC LXXXIX [1689]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:57178:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>March 26. 1689.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>Hen. Wharton, RR. in Chriſto P. ac</item>
                     <item>D. D. Wilhelmo, Archiep. Cant. à Sacris Domeſt.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57178:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED At St. <hi>Paul's Covent-Garden,</hi> On the Firſt <hi>Sunday</hi> in <hi>Lent;</hi> BEING A Second Part of the Sermon Preached before the <hi>Prince of Orange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>SYMON PATRICK,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Peterborough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Chiſwell,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's Church-Yard,</hi> MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:57178:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57178:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ISAIAH XI. 6.</bibl>
               <q>The Wolf alſo ſhall dwell with the Lamb, and the Leopard ſhall lye down with the Kid; and the Calf, and the young Lion, and the Fatling together; and a little Child ſhall lead them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Have already explained the Prophet's meaning in theſe words; which is, That Chriſt ſhould come, to make thoſe Men who were at as great odds as the <hi>Wolf</hi> and the <hi>Lamb,</hi> live in perfect Love and Peace together.</p>
            <p>Of this there is no queſtion, but only concerning the Truth of this Prophecy; which may ſeem not to have been fulfilled in our bleſſed Saviour; becauſe we ſee as bitter Enmities, and as bloody Contentions among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, as among other People.</p>
            <p>But though this be true, yet it is as true, that our Saviour is the Chriſt, in whom this Prophecy was accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed; as I undertook to demonſtrate from theſe <hi>Three</hi> Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>I. That it was the manifeſt deſign of our Saviour's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, to make ſuch Peace and Reconciliation among Mankind as is here deſcribed.</p>
            <p>II. That the nature of his Religion is ſuch, as is apt to produce this effect which he deſigned. And,</p>
            <p>III. That it was actually produced in the firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts to Chriſtianity, who heartily embraced his Religion.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:57178:3"/>
            <p>Of the two firſt of theſe I have largely diſcourſed, eſpecially of the <hi>ſecond.</hi> Wherein I ſhewed, That ſuch are the <hi>Principles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> of his Religion, which he requires us to believe: Such the <hi>Precepts</hi> which he recommends to our practice; and ſuch the <hi>Obligations</hi> he lays upon us, to believe theſe Principles, and practiſe theſe Precepts: That they could not fail of this End, to make Peace among Men, were they ſeriouſly conſidered, and heartily enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd.</p>
            <p>And that is ſaid in Scripture-language to be done by God, which he uſes ſufficient Means, and gives us ſufficient Power to bring to paſs; though the things ſhould not be actually effected. For God doth not intend to keep us in order and peace, like a Herd of Beaſts, by penning us up, and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us (as we do Lions and Tygers) ſo that it ſhall be out of our power to deſtroy and worry others; but he orders and governs us as reaſonable Creatures, who are to be reſtrained from doing hurt, by the <hi>knowledge of the Lord,</hi> as the Prophet explains himſelf <hi>Ver.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>If this enter into our Minds, and be rooted in our Hearts, it will alter our bruitiſh Natures, and chain up our furious Paſſions; nay, ſo mortifie and ſubdue them to the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of Chriſt, that we ſhall become new Creatures, transformed into the likeneſs of our Lord and Maſter, by whoſe Name we are called.</p>
            <p>This is enough to verifie what the Prophet ſaith: as I could ſhew by many unanſwerable Arguments, if it would not take up too much room in this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>But to give a fuller and more evident Satisfaction, I added the <hi>third</hi> Conſideration, which I could but lightly touch in the former Sermon, but ſhall now more largely
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57178:3"/> explain; and in concluſion add a <hi>fourth,</hi> which will expound this Prophecy in the moſt literal ſenſe that can be imagined.</p>
            <p>To put it then out of all doubt, that our bleſſed Lord is the Chriſt, who was to make <hi>the Wolf and the Lamb dwell together,</hi> let it be conſidered, That as it was his Intention to bring Men to Unity and Peace; and as the Nature of his Religion is ſuch, as is apt to produce this effect; ſo this effect was actually produced, in the firſt Converts to his Religion. All that were throughly indued with his Divine Knowledge, became the moſt love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Creatures in the World, and embraced one another with the moſt tender and ſincere Affection.</p>
            <p>And here it will be fit to conſider in the firſt place,</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>How <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> the Fore-runner of our Saviour, (who came, as I told you, <hi>to prepare his way,</hi> and <hi>to turn the hearts of the Fathers to the Children</hi>) began to work this happy Reconciliation among Men; and <hi>make ready,</hi> as the Angel ſaid he ſhould, <hi>a People prepared for the Lord.</hi> For he <hi>preaching the Baptiſm of Repentance for the remiſſion of Sins, Luk.</hi> 3. 3. great multitudes, of all ſorts of People, reſorted to him, and, with a common conſent, obeyed his Summons; even they who were as diſagreeing in their natures and diſpoſitions, as thoſe Creatures that are here mentioned in the Prophet.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Publicans,</hi> for inſtance, who were infamous for Extortion and cruel Oppreſſion, being as ravenous as <hi>evening Wolves</hi> (for that's the Character <hi>Zeno</hi> the Comedian gives of them, <hi>All Publicans are Harpyes</hi>) were taught by him to be as innocent as <hi>Lambs,</hi> by <hi>exacting no
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57178:4"/> more than that which was appointed them,</hi> in the publick Tables of Rates. Unto which all that received his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, gave their conſent, and engaged themſelves: For he admitted them unto Remiſſion of Sins upon no other terms, being far from flattering them with a falſe hope of finding Mercy with God, if they did not ceaſe their rapine, and unmerciful dealings with Men.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Soldiers</hi> likewiſe, Men as fierce as <hi>Leopards,</hi> and as rough as <hi>Bears,</hi> were diſciplin'd by him into a gentler Nature; like that of the <hi>Oxe</hi> and the <hi>Cow.</hi> For by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving his Baptiſm, they ſubmitted their Necks to that Yoke which he laid upon them, in this comprehenſive Precept, <hi>Do violence to no man, neither acouſe any falſely, and be content with your wages.</hi> Where he cautions them againſt their uſual Pillages, in extorting Money from the People; either by Threats and Terrors (as the firſt words ſignifie) or (as the next import) by pretended Reaſons; which, though never ſo falſe and abſurd, it is in vain to diſpute; as is wittily repreſented by <hi>Aeſop</hi> in the Fable of the <hi>Wolf and the Lamb</hi> (by which <hi>Grotius</hi> illuſtrates this paſſage) who came to drink at the ſame River. Where the cruel Beaſt accuſed the harmleſs Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for ſpoiling his draught, by troubling the Water; when he drank his fill at the top of the ſtream, before it came down to the innocent Lamb who ſtood below, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>People</hi> alſo were taught this Leſſon when they came to his Baptiſm, <hi>He that hath two coats, let him impart to him that hath none; and he that hath meat, let him do likewiſe;</hi> that is, let not others periſh by want, when you have more than needs. A moſt admirable and eaſie meaſure of Charity; <hi>to help others without harting our ſelves, to providef or their extreme Neceſſities, out of our Superfluities.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:57178:4"/>
               <p>Unto which it is to be ſuppoſed they alſo conſented when they were Baptized (that is, made Profeſſion of <hi>Repentance</hi>) as vaſt numbers of them were. Inſomuch that <hi>many of the Phariſees and the Sadduces came to his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> againſt whom he cries out, as <hi>a generation of Vipers;</hi> who had hearts as full of Rancour and Malice, as the Viper is of Poyſon; no leſs venomous than the <hi>Aſp and the Cockatrice</hi> mentioned in this Prophecy: And yet were ſo terrified at his Preaching, that they humbled themſelves to his Baptiſm; and there diſgorged their Venom, by confeſſing their Sins, and engaging (for it was not a bare acknowledging, but a renouncing them) to amend their lives, according to his Doctrine.</p>
               <p>All this you may read in the Third of St. <hi>Matthew</hi> and St. <hi>Luke;</hi> where they ſhew how the whole Nation flockt to him for Advice, what they ſhould do to <hi>flee from the wrath to come;</hi> and were inſtructed by him, to prepare themſelves, by ſuch means as theſe now mentioned, for the Kingdom of Chriſt; which he told them was approaching.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>Now what was thus begun by him, was further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted by our bleſſed Lord and Saviour, as ſoon as he appeared; when he taught all his Diſciples whom he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, <hi>Except ye be converted, and become as little children, ye cannot enter into the kingdom of heaven,</hi> Mat. 18. 3. that is, be made my Subjects, and be Partakers of their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. Accordingly all that profeſſed Subjection to him in ſinceriry, had their hearts thus converted and changed into that bleſſed temper of Spirit which he infuſed into his Diſciples, in his Sermon upon the Mount. Where he taught them to be humble, contented, tender-hearted,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57178:5"/> meek, merciful, peace-makers, pure in heart, patient; to lay aſide all anger, luſt, revenge, and whatſoever it is that troubles the World. And you read in the concluſion, That <hi>the people were aſtoniſhed at his doctrine, for he taught them as one having authority,</hi> Mat. 7. 29. or, as St. <hi>Luke</hi> expreſſes it upon another occaſion, <hi>Luk. 4. 32. his word was with power;</hi> having, no doubt, ſuch effect, as to work theſe qualities in many hearts; whereby their natures were altered, and turned into the ſimilitude of their Maſter, the Prince of Peace, who in his Life-time employed his Twelve Apoſtles in the ſame bleſſed Work, of making Peace among Men; And compares them to <hi>Lambs,</hi> when he ſent them to preach in <hi>Judea;</hi> which he tells them was to ſend them among a company of <hi>Wolves.</hi> For Men of ſuch Spirits there were then in that Nation; ſome of which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding were converted, and brought to live with them in a peaceable Subjection to the Government of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>But this Work was compleated, when the Holy Ghoſt came down from Heaven upon the Apoſtles on the Day of <hi>Pentecoſt;</hi> when ſome thouſands of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Proſelytes</hi> of ſeveral Nations were converted; not meerly to believe on Chriſt, but to live in the deareſt love and kindneſs one with another. So you read in <hi>Act. 2. 44, 45. And all that believed</hi> (who were Three thouſand converted at the firſt Sermon they preached) <hi>were together,</hi> that is, lived in perfect unity; <hi>and had all things common, and ſold their poſſeſſions and goods, and parted them to all men, as every man had need;</hi> that is, they did not barely abſtain from <hi>hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and deſtroying</hi> one another (as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> here ſaith they ſhould, <hi>ver.</hi> 9.) but were ſo kind as to do good, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57178:5"/> to each other, as their own abilities afforded, and their Neighbors neceſſities required.</p>
               <p>And this not for a fit only, but <hi>they continued daily with one accord in the temple, and did eat their meat with gladneſs and ſingleneſs of heart,</hi> ver. 46. that is, with Charity and Liberality unto others, whoſe wants called for their aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. For ſo a <hi>ſingle eye</hi> ſignifies, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 22. a chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table frank diſpoſition: And accordingly ſo a <hi>ſingle heart</hi> is to be here interpreted; a Mind free from covetous ſelfiſhneſs, purely bent to do good to others, and that with chearfulneſs: Which was the thing that <hi>gave them favour with all the people,</hi> as it there follows, <hi>ver.</hi> 44.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>Nor was this the effect of Chriſtianity in thoſe only that firſt received it; but you may obſerve, the ſame Spirit continued in thoſe that afterwards embraced it. For at the next great Converſion, which was made of Diſciples to Chriſt, you find that they being all filled with the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>the multitude of them that believed were of one heart, and of one ſoul,</hi> Act. 4. 32. In which was punctually fulfilled this Prophecy of <hi>Iſaiah:</hi> For though they were never ſo different in their Principles and Affections before, now they were ſo reconciled and united, as if there had been but one Heart or Spirit in ſuch a great multitude. And it is obſervable, that this Change was wrought <hi>in the holy mountain of God</hi> (as the Prophet predicts, <hi>ver.</hi> 9.) at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> where the Goſpel was firſt preached; and had this admirable effect in thoſe that entertained it, to make them conſpire together for their common good, as if they had been but one Man. <hi>For none of them ſaid that ought of the things he poſſeſſed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57178:6"/> was his own,</hi> but they had all things common (as it there follows) <hi>neither was there any among them that lacked; for as many as were poſſeſſors of lands or houſes ſold them, and brought the price of the things that were ſold, and laid them down at the Apoſtles feet; and diſtribution was made unto every man as he had need.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>After this indeed, <hi>when the number of the Diſciples was multiplied</hi> (as the Text ſpeaks, <hi>Act.</hi> 6. 1.) <hi>there aroſe a murmuring of the Grecians againſt the Hebrews, becauſe their widows were neglected in the daily miniſtration.</hi> But as this only ſignifies, that in ſuch a great company of Chriſtians, of which the body of the Church was made up, there were ſome ſo imperfectly inſtructed, that they retained ſome partiality of Spirit, and were too much inclined to favour particular Perſons, out of their near Relation and peculiar Affection to them, becauſe they were their Country-women, born in <hi>Judea,</hi> which the <hi>Grecians</hi> (though <hi>Jews</hi>) were not: So this very thing occaſioned a greater Unity, by the proviſion of a ſpeedy and moſt excellent remedy, which ſilenced theſe mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings for the preſent, and prevented them for the future. For the People are directed to find out <hi>ſeven</hi> Perſons from among themſelves, <hi>men of honeſt report, full of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and Wiſdom; whom the Apoſtles might appoint to attend upon this buſineſs.</p>
               <p>And it is very remarkable, that as this Propoſal <hi>pleaſed the whole multitude,</hi> ſo they all agreed by a common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, to make choice of <hi>Grecians</hi> only (as appears by their Names, <hi>ver.</hi> 5.) for this employment; who could not be ſuſpected of any want of tenderneſs for that party
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57178:6"/> which had been aggrieved. And accordingly after this, we hear of no more complaints about ſuch matters; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all Mens neceſſities were conſidered by theſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Perſons, with an equal reſpect, and fatherly care; to the general ſatisfaction both of thoſe who were born in <hi>Judea,</hi> and thoſe that were born in other Countries.</p>
               <p>And thus far you have ſeen only what concord there was among thoſe <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> who were converted to Chriſtianity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>But now, if we proceed to conſider what an happy agreement there was among Chriſtians, when the Church was enlarged ſo far, as to take in the whole Gentile World, it will convince every one that this Prophecy was exactly fulfilled.</p>
               <p>I. At the firſt opening of the door to let the <hi>Gentiles</hi> into the Fold of Chriſt, it muſt be acknowledged, that for a little ſpace there was ſome <hi>ſtrangeneſs,</hi> though no <hi>enmity,</hi> in the Converted Jews, unto the Gentile Chriſtians. They could not be perſuaded to converſe familiarly with them, much leſs to believe that the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles ſhould be made Partakers of the very ſame happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with themſelves; but they would have confined the Bleſſings of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> to their own Nation, or to their Rites of Religion.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtles themſelves were poſſeſſed with this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion at the firſt, by reaſon of the narrowneſs of their Minds; which were by degrees enlarged to contain more of the <hi>knowledge of the Lord.</hi> For as ſoon as a more full diſcovery was made to them of the Will of God, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57178:7"/> all their ſhineſs, in converſing with the Gentiles, vaniſhed; and they moſt joyfully cloſed with them, to make one Body, which edified it ſelf continually in love.</p>
               <p>This diſcovery was firſt made to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> who was ſent (as you read <hi>Act.</hi> 10.) to preach unto <hi>Cornelius,</hi> and other <hi>Gentiles,</hi> by a Voice that came to him from Heaven in a Viſion; wherein he ſaw <hi>all manner of four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>footed beaſts of the earth, and wild beaſts,</hi> &amp;c. and was bidden to eat of them indifferently, and no longer to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>that common which God had cleanſed;</hi> that is, as he afterward underſtood the meaning, not look upon the Gentiles as unclean Creatures; who were no longer to be avoided as Wolves and Leopards, and ſuch like Beaſts, but be made the Sheep of Chriſt. For the <hi>wild Beaſts</hi> as well as the <hi>tame,</hi> were all comprehended in that <hi>Sheet,</hi> which St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaw in the Viſion, let down from Heaven to the Earth.</p>
               <p>And therefore immediately upon this he went and preached to the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> and the Holy Ghoſt falling on them, even before they were Baptized, ſtopt the mouth of all Gain-ſayers, and perfectly ſilenced the <hi>Jews</hi> who had before diſputed againſt all Society and Converſation with them. So you read, <hi>Act.</hi> 11. where you find, <hi>ver. 2. they of the Circumciſion contended with Peter, ſaying, Thou wenteſt in to men uncircumciſed, and didſt eat with them,</hi> &amp;c. But when he had expounded to them the whole matter in order from the beginning (<hi>i. e.</hi> told them what In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions he had received from Heaven, whereby more of that Divine Knowledge which <hi>Iſaiah</hi> here ſpeaks of, was communicated to him) <hi>they hold their peace,</hi> ſaith the Story, <hi>ver. 18. and,</hi> more than that, <hi>they glorified God, ſaying, Then hath God alſo to the Gentiles granted repentance
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57178:7"/> unto life;</hi> that is, they owned them for the Children of God as much as themſelves, Heirs of the ſame Promiſes of Life and Bliſs; and accordingly laid aſide their ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and made no difference between themſelves and thoſe, whom they had lookt upon as unclean, and utterly unfit for their Society.</p>
               <p>II. And as the <hi>Jews</hi> were thus reconciled to the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> ſo were the <hi>Gentiles</hi> (I think I may ſay much more) reconciled to the <hi>Jews,</hi> though they had treated them formerly as unclean Creatures.</p>
               <p>1. This appears from their unheard of Charity towards the <hi>Jews,</hi> when they were in neceſſity; which was the higheſt Proof of a diſintereſted Affection. It would take up too much time to enumerate the places, where we read of the <hi>Collections</hi> which were made for the poor Chriſtians in <hi>Judea,</hi> in all Churches of the World which St. <hi>Paul</hi> planted, who himſelf ſometimes was at the pains to carry their Alms to <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> According to an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made between <hi>Peter</hi> and him, when the one went to preach to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the other to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> they took one another by the Hand to confirm this Agreement, and the only condition was, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>Gal. 2. 10. That we would remember the poor; the ſame which I alſo was forward to do.</hi> I gave you a famous inſtance of it in the <hi>Churches of Macedonia,</hi> who when they were in great Affliction themſelves, and in <hi>deep poverty</hi> (as S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s words are, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 2, 3, 4.) <hi>yet abounded in the riches of their liberality; for to their power, yea and beyond their power, they were willing of themſelves; praying us with much intreaty that we would receive the gift,</hi> &amp;c. which is a wonderful Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of that noble and high generoſity of Spirit, which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57178:8"/> Chriſtianity inſuſed into them: Little leſs marvellous than if one ſhould ſee an hungry Lyon or Wolf become ſo tame and tender-hearted, as to feed a feeble Lamb. For they were extremely poor themſelves, and yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the more preſſing neceſſities of their unknown Brethren. Unto whom they not only made a free-wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Offering, of their own accord, and with <hi>abundance of joy,</hi> but beſeeched the Apoſtle to receive it, and that with much earneſtneſs; as if it had been a favour to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to give help to others: The greateſt benefit to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be beneficial to their Brethren.</p>
               <p>2. Beſides this, their <hi>Hoſpitality</hi> was wonderful; which conſiſted in receiving Strangers, whom they never ſaw be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when they had occaſion to travel from one Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to another, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 13. If they brought Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nials along with them, that they were Chriſtians, they were freely entertained in Foreign Parts; and there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for, as Members of the ſame Body, with that Church to which they came: Who did not look upon them as Strangers, but as Friends; whom they treated with all imaginable kindneſs. This, no doubt, was one of the things that made the Heathen ſay, <hi>Behold how theſe Chriſtians love one another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. And it is further obſervable, that there were certain Perſons, who devoted themſelves to the Service of ſuch People; waſhing their Feet, when ſurbated or heated with their Travels; attending on them in their Sickneſs; and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imploying themſelves in ſuch like charitable offices: Which demonſtrated there was one Spirit that acted the whole Body, and made all the Chriſtian World one Communion. I have not room for all the places where theſe things are recorded: But you may read this plainly enough, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 1, 2.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57178:8"/> where <hi>Phebe</hi> it appears was ſuch a Perſon; <hi>a Servant of the Church of Cenchrea; i. e.</hi> one who miniſtred there to the Sick, and to the Poor, and had <hi>ſuccoured many,</hi> even St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, as he there acknowledges to her great honour. For the word he uſes ſignifies more than a meer <hi>Succourer</hi> or Helper: No leſs than a <hi>Patroneſs</hi> of him and others, whom ſhe had in a generous manner entertained out of her own Eſtate; and therefore upon that account is recommended by him to be kindly treated by the Roman Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>4. There were whole Colleges of pious Widows who devoted themſelves to ſuch Services, as thoſe men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in 1 <hi>Tim. 5. 10. bringing up children, lodging ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, waſhing the Saints feet, relieving the afflicted, and diligently following every good work.</hi> Which kindneſſes were more eſpecially ſhewn to thoſe who were baniſhed their own Countries, or deſpoiled of their Goods, and loſt their Friends, for Religion ſake. Unto whom the Promiſe of our Saviour was, by this means, literally made good, <hi>Mark 10. 29, 30. Verily I ſay unto you, there is no man that hath left houſe, or brethren, or ſiſters, or father, or mother, &amp;c. for my ſake and the goſpels, but he ſhall receive an hundred fold now in this time, houſes, and brethren, and ſiſters, and mothers, and children, and lands with perſecutions; and in the world to come eternal life.</hi> For every Country was their own Country; every Man's Lands were at their ſervice; for every Houſe they loſt upon our Saviour's ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, they had hundreds of Houſes to which they might reſort. For every Chriſtian's Houſe, was their Houſe; every one that belonged to Chriſt, was a Brother, and a Siſter to them; and many treated them with ſuch care and tenderneſs, as if they had been their own Child<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:57178:9"/>
               <p>And thus the words of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> were exactly fulfilled alſo; that People between whom there had been anciently the greateſt ſtrangeneſs, or rather antipathy, were now brought to ſuch a familiarity, that whereſoever they met they dwelt together in one another's Houſes; and there received ſuch a hearty welcom, as if they had been Domeſticks, born and bred up in that Family, which they had never ſeen before. By which means alſo the Goſpel was marvellouſly propagated, as is obſerved by <hi>Julian</hi> himſelf; who takes notice of this <hi>entertaining ſtrangers,</hi> as a moſt obliging Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; wherein Chriſtians quite out-did Heathens (who pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed no ſuch thing) and gain'd ground upon them every where.</p>
               <p>III. It muſt be confeſſed indeed, that after God had thus <hi>opened the door of faith to the Gentiles</hi> (as St. <hi>Luke</hi> writes, 14. 27.) there did ariſe a Controverſie; which, for ſome time, diſturbed the peace and quiet of thoſe Churches, which were planted among them; but it was admirably compoſed by the Wiſdom and Authority of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>Some of the Chriſtians in <hi>Judea,</hi> who were imperfect in the knowledg of the Goſpel (which muſt be diligently noted, becauſe where Men were fully inſtructed, there was no Contention about ſuch Matters) went abroad and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That, though the <hi>Gentiles</hi> did indeed belong to the Kingdom of Chriſt, and ſhould be made one Body with them; yet they muſt be Circumciſed, and tied to obſerve all the Rites and Ceremonies of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Law. Nay, they carried it ſo high, as to ſay, <hi>Except ye be circumoiſed after the manner of Moſes, ye cannot be ſaved,</hi> Act. 15. 1.</p>
               <p>They had the ſame Opinion, which the <hi>Jews</hi> are of at this day, That the <hi>reconciliation of the world</hi> one to another
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57178:9"/> ſhould be brought about, by uniting all Nations in the <hi>Moſaital</hi> Religion. Thus <hi>Maimonides</hi> expounds the words of this Prophet, as if by <hi>the Lyons eating ſtraw like an Oxe</hi> (in the Verſe following my Text) were meant the <hi>Gentiles</hi> eating only clean Meats, and abſtaining, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did, from all thoſe Creatures prohibited by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as unclean.</p>
               <p>About ſuch matters as theſe <hi>Paul and Barnabas had no ſmall diſſenſion and diſputation with them,</hi> ver. 2. that is, laboured to convince them (as we find by many Arguments he uſes in his Epiſtles) that all the World was to be made one; not by the obſerving their Law, but by the aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it; becauſe it was, in truth, a Wall of Partition and Separation between them and other Nations. Of which they could not be perſuaded preſently; popular Errors being very hard to be rooted out; and this was one of the chief. Which had ſo deeply rooted it ſelf in the Hearts of that Nation, that ſuch as were become Chriſtians ſtill retained it; and, through a partial ignorance remaining in them, ſtifly maintained, that <hi>Moſes</hi> his Law was to ſtand for ever; and that all Mankind muſt ſubmit unto it, or be ſhut out of the Kingdom of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>With this unreaſonable conceit they infected ſome of the <hi>Gentile</hi> Churches; though theſe things following were moſt evident.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> was given to that one Nation alone; and to be the Law of that one Land and Country only, and no other; and this, to keep them from the Idolatrous Cuſtoms of the People round about them. All this is apparent from the Law it ſelf, where you read, that <hi>Circumciſion</hi> (that great diſtinguiſhing Mark) was eſtabliſhed to be obſerved by <hi>Abraham and his ſeed, in their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57178:10"/> generations,</hi> Gen. 16. 7, 9. and that other Laws are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, a Statute <hi>throughout their generations,</hi> Levit. 7. 36. &amp; 24. 3. And this only in that particular Land or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, <hi>Deut. 4. 5. I have taught you ſtatutes and judgments, that ye ſhould do ſo in THE LAND whither you go to poſſeſs it.</hi> And again, <hi>ver. 14. The Lord commanded me at that time to teach you ſtatutes and judgments, that ye might do them in THE LAND whither ye go to poſſeſs it.</hi> And for this end alone, that they might be <hi>a holy people</hi> to him, that is, ſeparated from other Nations, and thereby pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from their wicked Cuſtoms. The places that men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this are ſo obvious, that I need not recite any of them: And it is apparent enough from thoſe now named, that all Nations were not concerned in thoſe Laws, but only the <hi>Jews;</hi> and they, only <hi>in the land of Canaan,</hi> not in other Countries; where they could not keep them. As the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves find by experience at this day, in the ſeveral Countries where they are diſperſed; in which they cannot obſerve all the Laws and Cuſtoms, which they were bound to obſerve there.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> And indeed it is impoſſible, that all thoſe Laws ſhould be obſerved by the whole <hi>Gentile</hi> World, OF by any that live in Countries much diſtant from <hi>Judea.</hi> For how ſhould <hi>they</hi> go up <hi>three times a year</hi> to worſhip at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (as all the Males among the <hi>Jews</hi> were bound) who live ſo far off from thence, that it would require a whole Year to make one Voyage thither? And how ſhould Women for their <hi>purification</hi> after Child-birth, and Lepers for their <hi>cleanſing,</hi> bring their Offering unto the Prieſt, to be preſented by him <hi>at the door of the taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of the congregation,</hi> Levit. 12. 14. Such things as theſe demonſtratively ſhew the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> was
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57178:10"/> 
                  <hi>local;</hi> that is, determined to a particular Country.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> But if it were poſſible to obſerve that Law, yet it would be unneceſſary; becauſe the reaſon of it is ceaſed by the coming of Chriſt: Who having aboliſhed that Idolatry which occaſioned the Law, might very well aboliſh the Law it ſelf; whoſe end was to keep them from the Manners of thoſe Nations which are now deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly</hi> and <hi>laſtly,</hi> It was far more reaſonable, that one Nation ſhould conform to the Common Law of all the World, than that all the World ſhould be conſtrained to conform to the Law of one Nation. Eſpecially ſince their Law was Arbitrary, depending wholly on the Will of the Law-giver, having no natural goodneſs in its Precepts: But the Laws of Chriſt are little elſe, than the plain dictates of reformed Nature; ſuch as all Mankind, if they were themſelves, would chuſe to obſerve, though Chriſt had not given them.</p>
               <p>Such Reaſons as theſe, no doubt, ſatisfied the wiſeſt and beſt Chriſtians; and as for the reſt, the Apoſtles took an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable courſe to compoſe the differences they had made in the Church, by that moſt prudent Decree which we read in the ſame <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 20, 28, 29. That the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> to maintain Peace and Unity with the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſhould for the preſent abſtain from a few things which were moſt offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to them, particularly <hi>eating blood, and things ſtrangled:</hi> Which was no great abridgment of their Liberty; and therefore the <hi>Gentiles</hi> chearfully conſented to it, becauſe they ſaw it would be an effectual means to ſettle them in Quietneſs and Peace.</p>
               <p>For this Decree being firſt ſent to the Chriſtians of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> where the Controverſie began, they <hi>rejoyced for the conſolation,</hi> ver. 31. And being afterward delivered to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57178:11"/> every Church where the Apoſtles travelled to preach the Goſpel; <hi>So were the Churches eſtabliſhed in the faith, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed in number daily,</hi> Act. 16. 4, 5. that is, they were ſetled in the right Belief, that none of thoſe things were neceſſary which the <hi>Jews</hi> urged them to obſerve (ſave only for Peace ſake) and by that means a great many other <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> finding no ſuch burthen ſhould be laid upon them, came and joyned themſelves to the <hi>Chriſtian Society.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is true, ſome of the <hi>Jews</hi> ſtill made a diſturbance, as we may gueſs from ſome Paſſages in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Epiſtles:</hi> But they were dreadfully confuted by the Deſtruction of the Temple, and whole Commonwealth of the <hi>Jews;</hi> which made it impoſſible for them to obſerve all the Rites and Cuſtoms for which they contended, though they were in <hi>Judea;</hi> and laid this Controverſie aſleep, or rather dead, among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> for ever.</p>
               <p>You will ſay, perhaps, that other Queſtions and Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences aroſe, which troubled the Church. And it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that the Apoſtles themſelves complain of ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable and abſurd Men, who taught perverſe things; and alſo foretold, That after their deceaſe, <hi>grievous Wolves would enter in among them, not ſparing the flcok,</hi> Act. 20. 29. But ſtill, by their Care and Authority, the main body of the Flock of Chriſt were kept in perfect Peace and Quiet, or differed more in ſome Opinions, than in their Affections! And after their departure out of this World, they ſo continued, under the conduct of Apoſtolical Men; who watched over their Flocks with ſuch diligence, that thoſe <hi>Wolves did little hurt;</hi> all that Sophiſtry being powerfully baffled by them, wherewith thoſe peſtilent Men ſubverted ſome weak Minds, and drew them into their ſenſeleſs Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies. For, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> it was
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57178:11"/> needleſs to write to them touching Brotherly Love; becauſe <hi>they themſelves were taught of God to love one another, 1 Theſſ.</hi> 4. 9. ſo it is reaſonable to preſume the ſame of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of all other Chriſtians in thoſe days. And in the following Ages, their Love, as I obſerved before, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſome Sects among them, was ſo notorious, that it ſet <hi>a mark upon them</hi> (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeaks) and made<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apolog. c.</hi> 39.</note> the Heathen ſay, <hi>See how they love one another.</hi> For the Heathen were not more prone to kill thoſe whom they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, than the Chriſtians were to lay down their own Lives, for to ſave their <hi>Brethren.</hi> So they called one another, as he ſays, in his days, having all one Father, being born again in one laver of Regeneration; and drinking of one Spirit of Holineſs (as his words are,) which inſpired them with ſuch Charity, that they were kindly affectioned towards the moſt froward and peeviſh People; and, as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> tells the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> whether they would or no, lookt upon them as their <hi>Brethren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus, I may preſume, I have ſufficiently proved, how peaceable and quiet the Kingdom of Chriſt was, when he firſt began to Reign: What a marvellous Change he made in the World: How he reconciled their Enmities, and made them depoſite their Hatreds: Inclined them to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace one another with ſuch an unuſual Affection, and to take ſuch a care of each others Welfare, that it made the Chriſtian Society to be admired by thoſe who were not of it; and invited great numbers, in the moſt dangerous days, to enter into it.</p>
               <p>That things did not continue in this bleſſed ſtate ſo long as might have been expected, is to be imputed to thoſe <hi>vain Talkers</hi> who perverted the plain, ſimple Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, and turned it into <hi>another Goſpel;</hi> till
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57178:12"/> at laſt there was ſuch a foul Apoſtaſie as we now ſee in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Where great numbers of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are become <hi>Wolves, Leopards</hi> and <hi>Tygers</hi> again; who, for many Ages, have ravaged and devoured the harmleſs <hi>Lambs</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt. For a moſt <hi>beaſtly Cruelty</hi> entred into the Church, together with a profound <hi>Ignorance;</hi> according to the Obſervation of the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> (which will ever be true) <hi>The dark places of the earth are full of the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of cruelty,</hi> Pſal. 74. 20.</p>
               <p>For the firſt Three hundred Years and more, there was not the leaſt ſign of a perſecuting Spirit; though there were ſuch horrid Opinions then vented, as have not been heard of in theſe later times. But Chriſtians, being then wholly unacquainted with Force and Violence one towards another, beat them down with Spiritual Weapons; by which they maintained the Faith of Chriſt in ſincerity, and got a glorious Victory over thoſe mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Hereſies. Impoſitions upon Mens Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and forcing their Belief, or at leaſt the Profeſſion of Articles of Faith, by inflicting corporal Puniſhments merely for falſe Opinions, came in with the Retinue and Train of Antichriſt; that is, crept into the Church, as other Abuſes and Corruptions did, when the firſt warmths of Chriſtianity were abated, and <hi>the charity of many was waxed cold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as this was foretold by our bleſſed Saviour and his Apoſtles, ſo they aſſure us, That the lofty Pretences of this Apoſtate Church ſhall one day be thrown down: And that with the Deſtruction of this <hi>myſtical Babylon,</hi> the Chriſtian World ſhall be renewed. <hi>A new Jeruſalem ſhall come down from heaven</hi> (as St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 3, 4.) <hi>and the tabernacle of God ſhall be with men, and he
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57178:12"/> will dwell with them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and God ſhall wipe away all tears from their eyes; and there ſhall be no more death, neither ſorrow, nor crying</hi> (or <hi>bawling,</hi> as the word ſignifies) <hi>neither ſhall there be any more pain</hi> (or <hi>toil</hi> rather, and <hi>drudgery) for the former things are done away;</hi> that is, Oppreſſion and Cruelty ſhall be Strangers to this Church; there ſhall be no haleing Men to the Stake; no la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting over thoſe that are butchered; no bawling, Away with them, they are not worthy to live; no condemning Men to the Gallies; no painful tugging at the Oars, and ſuch like Barbarities: But Chriſtians ſhall live at eaſe, and be ſo kind one to another, that there ſhall be nothing but Joy in God, and in their mutual Charity; for, in one word, <hi>former things,</hi> ſuch as we now ſee, ſhall be ſo baniſhed from the Chriſtian World, that they ſhall be known only by hear-ſay.</p>
               <p>I cannot now further enlarge upon this, becauſe I have one thing more to add for the Explication of this Prophecy; which as it will anſwer the moſt literal ſenſe of it, ſo is very ſuitable to the preſent ſeaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>The groſſer ſort of <hi>Jews,</hi> I told you, in the beginning of this Diſcourſe, would have us underſtand by <hi>Wolves, Leopards,</hi> and <hi>Lyons,</hi> &amp;c. the very Beaſts that bear theſe Names: which in the days of Chriſt they fanſy ſhall become tame, and made as gentle and familiar as thoſe we call <hi>Oxen, Calves</hi> and <hi>Lambs.</hi> There is great reaſon, I ſhewed you, againſt this Interpretation: but if any be ſo ſtubborn as to ſtick to it, and will not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57178:13"/> believe, unleſs we ſhew him when this was done: I think it is not difficult to give him ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>For St. <hi>Mark</hi> tells us, That when our bleſſed Saviour was in the Wilderneſs <hi>forty days</hi> tempted of the Devil (of which St. <hi>Matthew</hi> gives us a larger Account in the Goſpel for this day) <hi>he was with the wild Beaſts, and the Angels miniſtred unto him,</hi> Mark 1. 13. The Devil, that is, attempted to affright him with ſuch terrible Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as the <hi>Lyons, Wolves,</hi> and <hi>Tygers;</hi> which are greedy of Man's Fleſh, as well as of other Creatures: But none of theſe had any power to annoy him. Quite contrary, they all lickt his Feet (as I may ſpeak) and were as innocent and as gentle as the <hi>Lambs.</hi> For that muſt be the ſenſe of theſe words [<hi>He was with the wild Beaſts</hi>] he was in the midſt of them; and that without any harm at all; they being as mild in his preſence, as thoſe we count the meekeſt Creatures.</p>
               <p>In this the power of our Saviour began to diſcover it ſelf to the Devil; who ſaw this Prophecy literally fulfilled in him, <hi>The Wolf ſhall dwell with the Lamb,</hi> &amp;c. and that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91. 13. <hi>Thou ſhalt tread upon the Lyon and the Adder, the young Lyon and the Dragon ſhalt thou trample under thy feet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet, ſuch is the bold and reſtleſs nature of the Tempter, when he could not terrifie him by this horrid company of wild Beaſts, he had the confidence to hope for an advantage, from hence, another way. For he imagined our Saviour himſelf would take the confidence, by this Authority and Power which he found he could exerciſe over thoſe fierce Creatures, to preſume to do ſome other ſtrange thing, without the ſame reaſon: Eſpecially when
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57178:13"/> Scripture might ſeem to encourage to it, even that very Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture which I now named.</p>
               <p>Accordingly the Devil takes our Saviour into the holy City, and ſets him on a Pinnacle of the Temple, and ſaith, <hi>If thou be the Son of God, caſt thy ſelf down; for it is written, He ſhall give his Angels charge concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee; and in their hands they ſhall bear thee up, leſt at any time thou daſh thy foot againſt a ſtone,</hi> Mat. 4. 6. If you enquire where this <hi>is written,</hi> the Anſwer to it will acquaint you with a thing very remarkable. For it is written in the ſame Pſalm, where you find the other words I now alledged, <hi>Thou ſhalt tread upon the Lyon and the Adder,</hi> &amp;c. and, the truth is, goes imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately before them in this manner, <hi>For he ſhall give his Angels charge over thee, to keep thee in all thy ways; they ſhall bear thee up in their hands, leſt thou daſh thy foot againſt a ſtone. Thou ſhalt tread upon the Lyon and Adder; the young Lyon and the Dragon ſhalt thou trample under thy feet.</hi> Now they being thus connected and knit together, our Saviour durſt not ſeparate them, as Men, in theſe days, are bold to do with the holy Scriptures. Which he underſtood ſo perfectly, that he could not be cheated with the Devil's Sophiſtry: For he knew the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> was to be thus expounded (as an<note place="margin">Doctor <hi>Jackſon.</hi>
                  </note> eminent Divine of ours hath long ago obſerved) That the Angels ſhould keep him if he <hi>trod upon a Lyon or an Adder</hi> as they came in his way <hi>in the Wilderneſs;</hi> as well as <hi>bear him up,</hi> that he ſhould not <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh his foot againſt a ſtone.</hi> And ſo they did; for <hi>the Angels mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred unto him,</hi> while he was with the wild Beaſts; upon whom if he had trod, it had been no tempting of God; becauſe he had promiſed to ſend his Angels
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57178:14"/> to guard him from harm in that action. But they had no ſuch Commiſſion, that he could find, to keep him if he <hi>caſt himſelf headlong from the pinnacle of the temple:</hi> For it was no part of <hi>his way,</hi> as it was to be <hi>in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs,</hi> whither the <hi>Spirit carried him.</hi> Nor was it a thing included in this Promiſe, which ſignifies only thus much, That all Creatures ſhould be obedient unto him; and though never ſo fierce and virulent in their own nature, ſhould loſe their Power and their Poiſon in his preſence.</p>
               <p>Thus, I think, the words of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> were in the moſt literal ſenſe of them, made good to the full.</p>
               <p>And it may be obſervable, perhaps, that as this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy in my Text immediately follows a Prediction, That Chriſt, the <hi>branch of the ſtock of Jeſſe,</hi> ſhould be filled with the Spirit, <hi>ver.</hi> 2, 3. <hi>The ſpirit of the Lord ſhall reſt upon him, the ſpirit of wiſdom and underſtanding, the ſpirit of counſel,</hi> &amp;c. So our Saviour's <hi>being with the wild Beaſts,</hi> immediately followed after the <hi>deſcent of the Holy Ghoſt upon him</hi> at his Baptiſm; as the <hi>three</hi> firſt Evangeliſts tell us, who write about this matter; parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly St. <hi>Mark</hi> in the place before named, ſaith, <hi>Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately the ſpirit driveth him into the wilderneſs;</hi> that is, as ſoon as ever he was Baptized, and the Holy Spirit, with a Voice from Heaven, was come down upon him, he was led by the Spirit into deſart places, <hi>and there he was with the wild Beaſts,</hi> Mark 1. 12, 13. And then came to paſs what <hi>Iſaiah</hi> had foretold, That there was no difference between a <hi>Lyon</hi> and a <hi>Lamb,</hi> a <hi>Leopard</hi> and a <hi>Kid,</hi> an <hi>Aſp</hi> and a <hi>ſucking Child;</hi> but they were all alike ſubject to our bleſſed Lord and Saviour.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:57178:14"/>
               <p>There is one Objection that may be made againſt what I have ſaid; which ſeems to lye againſt <hi>the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention</hi> of our Saviour: Which was not, may ſome fanſy, to make Peace in the World: but he himſelf ſaith, <hi>I came not to ſend peace, but a ſword;</hi> I am come to <hi>ſet a man at variance againſt his father, and the daughter againſt her mother,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 34, 35, 36. Or as St. <hi>Luke</hi>'s words are, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 51. <hi>Suppoſe ye that I am come to give peace on earth? I tell you, Nay; but rather diviſion.</hi> This I thought good to mention; though ſuch Paſſages, I hope, are now ſo well underſtood, that a ſhort Anſwer will ſerve to it. For,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is evident from plainer places, That our Lord did come to ſend Peace; and he was not ſo weak as to contradict himſelf. What can be plainer than thoſe words of his, <hi>Peace I leave with you, my peace I give,</hi> or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, <hi>unto you?</hi> Joh. 14. 27.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> And on the other ſide it is as manifeſt, He intended nothing leſs than to bring a Sword, and to make War: For he forbad his Diſciples to <hi>take the Sword;</hi> and commanded them to pray for their Enemies, not to kill them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Therefore he cannot be thought to ſpeak <hi>of his intention</hi> (when he ſaith, <hi>I came to ſend a ſword; or diviſion</hi>) but of the <hi>event</hi> of his coming <hi>by accident.</hi> Juſt as we ſay, when we give a Friend a Viſit out of meer kindneſs, <hi>I am come to trouble you:</hi> Not that we deſign any trouble to him, but are afraid it may prove ſo, at that time, if he be otherwiſe engaged. In like manner doth our Saviour ſay, he came to bring a Sword,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57178:15"/> and to make variance: Not becauſe he would have it ſo, but becauſe he foreſaw many Men were ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined another way, and ſo ſtrongly engaged in other Perſuaſions, that they would not only refuſe his Religion, but quarrel with them that received it.</p>
               <p>This was the <hi>diviſion</hi> he ſpeaks of: They who did not become Chriſtians, he knew, would hate and malign thoſe that did; and that a great deal more, than if they had remained ſtill Heathens or Jews. Which was not the drift or the effect of his Doctrine; but proceeded from their ignorance of it; by refuſing to entertain it; nay, wilfully ſhutting their eyes againſt that light of Divine Knowledge; <hi>which filled the earth, as the waters cover the ſea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To be brief: This only proves what I diſcourſed in the former Sermon, That Mankind muſt uſe their ſincere endeavours to make themſelves happy, through the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Jeſus Chriſt; or elſe they may become more miſerable by that very means. The buſineſs will not do of it ſelf, but we muſt contribute our pains and labour to bring it about; by a faithful improvement of thoſe means which God affords us of Knowledge and of Grace.</p>
               <p>So the Prophet, I ſhew'd you, explains his own mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and ſo the ſober Jews themſelves underſtand him; particularly <hi>Matmonides,</hi> who ſaw very well, that if he had ſaid otherwiſe, he ſhould have been in danger to be confuted by other places of the Old Scriptures; where there are the like Promiſes to the Jewiſh Nation, which did not come to paſs, becauſe of their refractory diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And yet the Promiſes were true, becauſe God did
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57178:15"/> what he intended and engaged, to effect that Bleſſing for them. Read <hi>Jer.</hi> 32. 37, 39, where he promiſes to give them <hi>one heart, and one way;</hi> and ſo he did, by diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing things in ſuch a manner at their return from <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> as to take away the cauſes of all their differences. And yet they ſtill continued at odds, as much as ever; becauſe they did not receive that heart which he gave them; by diſpoſing themſelves to make a good uſe of his wonderful Providence; which ordered all things to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur, for the making a bleſſed accord among them.</p>
               <p>Which that it may not prove our own caſe, let us ſeriouſly conſider, that Chriſt will not abſolutely force his Favours upon us; for that's directly contrary both to the Goſpel, and to the Law of the Jews alſo: Which ſuppoſe that Men may refuſe what he deſigns to beſtow upon them, nay, puts into their hands. For both of them threaten Men ſeverely, if they be ſo croſs as to walk contrary unto him, who would do them good: And therefore the iſſue of this long Diſcourſe is, That we muſt do our part to make our Selves and the World happy.</p>
               <p>We muſt be ſenſible of the infinite Love of God; we muſt thankfully receive the Goſpel; we muſt heartily believe it, and ſtudy it, and apply our ſelves to obſerve it; we muſt regard alſo the Works of Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which hath a Voice and ſpeaks loudly, as well as his Word; and not expect to be made happy like a company of wild Beaſts, who are kept by mere violence from deſtroying others. No, if we will not <hi>ſhew our ſelves men,</hi> as this Prophet ſpeaks, we ſhall, after ſuch extraordinary means, as God hath uſed for our amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, become ſo much the more bruitiſh; more fierce and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57178:16"/> violent, like Lyons and Tygers, by being under diſcipline, but not ſubdued by it.</p>
               <p>For when Men <hi>hold the truth of God in unrighteouſneſs,</hi> he delivers them up to a reprobate mind; ſo that they become not mere Beaſts, but worſe than Beaſts; for Beaſts do not act ſuch things, as the Apoſtle there ſays ſome Men committed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 18, 26, 27, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Beaſts follow the uſe of Nature, and are generally favourable to thoſe of the ſame kind with themſelves: But they who pervert the Knowledge of God, forſake, in time, the natural uſe, and, as the Proverb is, <hi>One Man becomes a Wolf to another Man:</hi> Nay, according to another ancient Saying, <hi>They become ſo many Devils one to another;</hi> to vex and torment each other, without end.</p>
               <p>Let this move us therefore to apply our minds to the ſtudy of making our ſelves and the World happy; by an hearty entertainment of the Chriſtian Religion: and then it is heartily entertained, when it makes us love God, and one another.</p>
               <p>Do your beſt to bring back thoſe comfortable and truly glorious days, when Chriſtians were <hi>of one heart, and of one ſoul.</hi> Lay aſide, or rather bury all your Enmities and Hatreds; put away Strife and Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ceafe from anger, and let go wrath; let no cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, no evil ſpeaking be heard among you; much leſs ſuch evil ſpeaking as St. <hi>Jude</hi> charges upon ſome ungodly Men, who <hi>ſpake evil of dignities;</hi> ver. 8. and ſpake evil of thoſe things, which <hi>they knew not,</hi> ver. 10.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:57178:16"/>
               <p>Wreſt this Prophecy out of the hands of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who will not believe what is written in the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> concerning the Unity of Chriſt's Diſciples. Therefore let them now ſee ſuch Unity among us; by the Change of our fierce and violent Natures, into a Lamb-like Diſpoſition. Confute all their Objections; and leave them not the ſhadow of an Argument againſt our Religion. Convince them that <hi>Jeſus</hi> is the <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by the Innocence and Unblamableneſs of your Lives; by your Love and Charity; by ſubduing all your unruly Appetites and Deſires; by taming your furious and outragious Paſſions; by purging out your Choler and Gall, all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Malice, and deſire of Revenge; by becoming like <hi>the ſucking Child,</hi> of which <hi>Iſaiah</hi> here ſpeaks: Who is without Guile, without Ambition, Covetouſneſs, Pride, Hatred, or any other Quality; whereby the World is now miſerably divided and diſturbed.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, You muſt be like little Children in all things, but only <hi>in underſtanding:</hi> for therein, you muſt <hi>be Men,</hi> as the Apoſtle inſtructs you, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> xiv. 20. <hi>Brethren, be not children in underſtanding: howbeit, in malice be ye children; but in underſtanding be men.</hi> And truly, that's the way to be like Children <hi>in malice</hi> (that is, to have none at all) <hi>in underſtanding</hi> to be Men. For the more thorowly we know the Will of God in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> the more loving and peaceable, as well as juſt and pure we ſhall be. We ſhall make it our Buſineſs to do good to all, but hurt to none; no not to our Enemies, and ſuch as do hurt to us. And therefore fill your Minds with a ſolid Knowledge of your Duty, and not with Notions meerly, or aiery Speculations; which ſerve only for Talk, and perhaps for Wranglings and Diſputes.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:57178:17"/>
               <p>There is a Knowledge, I muſt here mind you, which will hinder the fulfilling of this Prophecy; for it makes Men fall out and quarrel one with another; nay, hate all thoſe who are not of their Mind and Way. But this is not the <hi>Knowledge of the Lord:</hi> which as it is the Wiſdom that is pure, <hi>the Knowledge of the Holy;</hi> ſo it is the <hi>Meekneſs of Wiſdom,</hi> the <hi>Way of Peace.</hi> For it is the Knowledge of God's great Love to us in <hi>Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus;</hi> and the Knowledge of that Love and Obedience we owe to him; and of that extraordinary Kindneſs we ought to have one for another.</p>
               <p>In this Knowledge let us grow and increaſe daily; and not be like to thoſe of whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> complains; who <hi>doted about Queſtions, and ſtrifes of Words, whereof cometh Envy, Strife, Railing, evil Surmiſings, &amp;c.</hi> I. Tim. vi. 4. I take it to be very remarkable, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle cautions <hi>Timothy five</hi> or <hi>ſix</hi> times againſt this wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Religion: which ſpent its time in Queſtions, Doubts, and Arguings, about many uſeleſs Notions; that tended to nothing but to fill Mens Minds with a falſe Opinion of Knowledge, and to embroil the Church with Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes that could never be determined; or, if they could, it was never the more edified thereby either in Faith or Piety. He begins with this Charge, I. Tim. i. 4. <hi>Not to give heed to Fables, and endleſs Genealogies, which miniſter Queſtions, rather than godly edifying, which is in Faith.</hi> The critical Notion of which Words, [<hi>Fables and Genealogies</hi>] is not to be expected in this Diſcourſe: It is ſufficient to know, that he means by <hi>Fables</hi> not only <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>doubtful</hi> Relations, which rely upon no certain Tradition, but ſuch as were <hi>idle</hi> alſo, if they had been true; becauſe they ſerved for nothing but to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:57178:17"/> fill Mens Minds with unprofitable Thoughts, and to keep out better Things. Which was the fault alſo of that endleſs Pains, which the falſe Apoſtles took to derive their Pedigree from the ancient Patriarchs (which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may be meant by <hi>Genealogies.</hi>) For they neither made Men a jot wiſer, nor more holy: neither improv'd their Minds, nor reformed their Wills and Affections: Which is the great thing that the Goſpel deſigns, as he ſhews in the following Words (where he tells what kind of Knowledge we ſhould enquire after) <hi>the end of the Commandment, i. e.</hi> the Deſign of the Goſpel, <hi>is Charity,</hi> the Love of God and of our Neighbour; which ſprings <hi>out of a pure Heart,</hi> purged from all ſenſual Affections and <hi>Paſſions, and a good Conſcience,</hi> that aims only at being truly void of offence towards God and Man; which ariſes out <hi>of Faith unfeigned;</hi> that is, a <hi>ſincere</hi> Belief of the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the ſame effect he admoniſhes him again, iv. 7. <hi>Refuſe profane and old wives Fables, and exerciſe thy ſelf rather unto Godlineſs:</hi> Where it is evident he ſpeaks of ſuch Diſcourſes, as not only buſied Mens Minds to no purpoſe; but hindred them from being better im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, in ſerviceable Actions of Piety, Mercy, and other Chriſtian Vertues.</p>
               <p>And as in theſe two Places he oppoſes <hi>Piety</hi> to this ſort of Knowledge, ſo he doth in a <hi>third,</hi> which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore named, vi. 3, 4, 5. where he deſcribes thoſe who <hi>doted about Questions and Strifes of Words,</hi> as Men that <hi>conſented not to wholeſom Words, even the Words of our Lord Jeſus, and to the Doctrine which is according unto Godlineſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:57178:18"/>
               <p>Which he repeats again, when he writes a ſecond time to him, in the next Epiſtle, ii. 22, 23. <hi>Flee youthful Luſts: but follow Righteouſneſs, Faith, Charity, Peace, with them that call on the Lord out of a pure Heart. But fooliſh, and unlearned Queſtions avoid, knowing that they gender ſtrifes. And the Servant of the Lord muſt not ſtrive; but be gentle unto all men, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By which you ſee, that this is a Knowledge rather to be rooted out, than planted and cheriſhed: though, alas! it hath been ſo diligently cultivated, that it hath <hi>covered the Earth, as the Waters cover the Sea:</hi> which the ſaving Knowledge of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ought to have done. The World hath been filled with Queſtions, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies: and Men have thought themſelves wiſe, when they had learnt to argue and wrangle about them. On this they have ſet their Hearts; as if it were all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or the moſt conſiderable part thereof. <hi>But to what end do we contend</hi> (as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> honeſtly gloſſes upon the firſt of theſe Places, I. <hi>Tim.</hi> i. 6.) <hi>whether Sin be a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation only, or a Spot which ſticks to the Soul? Let this rather be the Work of a Divine, to perſuade all Men to abhor and hate every Sin. We diſpute whole Ages, whether that Grace with which God loveth and draweth us, be the ſame with that, wherewith we love him again? whether it be ſomething created, or increated? Let us make this our Buſineſs rather, that hy pure Prayers, by Innocence of Life, by pious Actions, we may obtain the Favour of God, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow his Grace upon us. We ſquabble without end, what it is that diſtinguiſhes the Father from the Son, and both of them from the Holy Ghoſt; whether a Thing, or a Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and how they can be Three, when they are One Eſſence? How much more pertinent would it be, by all means to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:57178:18"/> that we may piouſly and holily worſhip and adore that TRINITY, whoſe Majeſty is inſcrutable; and by our Concord and Agreement expreſs, to our power, their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effable Concord: that ſo at length we may be admitted into their Bleſſed Fellowſhip for ever? &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This indeed is a Contention moſt worthy of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to ſtrive who ſhall have moſt Charity; and be the forwardeſt to come to an amicable Agreement, and make a friendly End of all their Differences. In this we are truly <hi>Followers,</hi> or Imitators, <hi>of God:</hi> whoſe great Deſign in ſending his Son, with the Goſpel of his Grace to us, was to reconcile us unto himſelf, and one unto another. If both be not wrought, neither of them is: nor is it poſſible for us to ſee happy days, unleſs there be an Accord among us: In order to which, we muſt, among other things, avoid that contentious and quarrelſom ſort of Knowledge; by which Men loſe not only their Charity, but, too often, their Faith alſo; and diſpute themſelves into Irreligion.</p>
               <p>Which is ſo neceſſary a Caution, that the Apoſtle, I obſerve, mentions it once more, in the concluſion of his firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> vi. 20, 21. <hi>O Timothy, keep that which is committed to thy truſt</hi> (the Doctrine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Godlineſs, before mentioned, <hi>v.</hi> 3.) <hi>avoiding profane and vain bablings, and oppoſitions of Science falſly ſo called: which ſome profeſſing, have erred concerning the Faith.</hi> The way to <hi>keep</hi> the one, is to <hi>avoid</hi> the other: For by refuſing to engage our ſelves in <hi>vain Bablings</hi> and <hi>Oppoſitions,</hi> in <hi>contradicting</hi> one another, and in <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe,</hi> or prepoſterous, <hi>Diſputations,</hi> (as the Apoſtle calls them, <hi>v.</hi> 5.) we ſhall have the more time to beſtow in ſetling the ſolid Knowledge of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and of our
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:57178:19"/> Chriſtian Duty, not only in our Minds, but in our Hearts. Which will give us ſuch ſatisfaction, that we ſhall not be willing to have it diſturbed by angry Diſputes, ſharp Contentions, and fierce Conflicts one with another: but (to ſpeak in the Language of my Text) we ſhall be as meek and quiet as <hi>Lambs,</hi> though of never ſuch diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Opinions; and have nothing at all of the <hi>Wolf</hi> in us, leſt if we <hi>bite and devour one another, we be conſumed one of another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our preſent Oppoſitions and Conteſts indeed are of another ſort, than thoſe in the Apoſtles Times: but they have the ſame ill Effect, to hinder better things; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that Thankfulneſs we ought to have for God's Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, and that Chriſtian Unity and Concord, for which all good Men wiſh, and in their ſeveral ways endeavour. Give me leave therefore, with reſpect to our preſent Circumſtances, to ſuggeſt a few things, which may help to lead us into the way of Peace.</p>
               <p>Beſides the Knowledge of the Nature of God, and of his Love in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and of the Nature of Religion, eſpecially of Chriſtianity, and the principal Doctrines of it, particularly thoſe two great Commandments, of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God above all things, and our Neighbour as our ſelves: it might do us ſome ſervice, if we would la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to <hi>know our ſelves</hi> better; and to <hi>underſtand the Nature of Things;</hi> and reflect frequently upon the <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge we have of former Times.</hi> Briefly of theſe <hi>Three.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I. Firſt, The Knowledge of our ſelves would teach us, That Men do not differ more in their Countenances, than they do in the Frame of their Underſtandings; And therefore we muſt not ſpend our pains in making all Men think alike; for it is impoſſible to be effected.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:57178:19"/> But while we differ in our Thoughts, the Knowledge of our ſelves would ſoon make us ſenſible, we are not ſuch conſiderable Creatures, that it becomes us to be confident in the Opinions, wherein we claſh one againſt another. If we be, we ſhould conſider, that others may think they have as great reaſon to be confident in their Perſuaſion, as we are in ours: and that they differ no further from us, than we do from them: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, why ſhould we not bear one with another, which is the way of Peace, when Friends cannot agree? Nay, why ſhould we not entirely love one another, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſuch Differences? Since there is no more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for our hating them, than there is for their hating us: the Oppoſition being equal on both ſides. For juſt ſo much as they are againſt us, we are againſt them: and there is no more we have to bear withal in them, than they have to bear withal in us.</p>
               <p>II. <hi>Secondly,</hi> If we underſtood the <hi>Nature of Things</hi> a little better, we ſhould the ſooner agree to this. For we ſhould find, that ſome Things are of very great difficulty; about which there will be ever ſuch variety of Judgment, that it is not becoming any of us to be too confident. All Things likewiſe are not of equal moment; and therefore we ought to make a difference, and not contend for every thing alike. There are Things alſo out of our way, which belong not properly to our Cognizance: in which it is a good Rule, <hi>Every Man muſt be believed in his own Art.</hi> In Matters of Law, <hi>Divines</hi> have as much reaſon to relie upon good. <hi>Lawyers;</hi> as <hi>Lawyers</hi> have in Matters of Religion, to relie upon good <hi>Divines:</hi> Not with an abſolute Reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, but with a modeſt Deference to their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:57178:20"/> in their own Faculties. If able Men of either Faculty be of different Judgments, that's a Reaſon to be moderate in our Opinions, and in our Cenſures, and in all our Behaviour: and not to judge ill, much leſs ſpeak ill of thoſe that differ from us, in things wherein the wiſeſt Men are not agreed.</p>
               <p>To ſpeak freely, the things that at preſent diſtract us, are either our Concerns as we are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> or as we are <hi>Engliſhmen:</hi> our <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> or our <hi>Civil</hi> Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Now, as to the former, there is ſuch a Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on one ſide to yield to the weakneſs of their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; that if they, on the other ſide, will be ſatisfied without breaking the very Conſtitution, I do not ſee how we can fail to come to an happy Agreement. All the difficulty is about the other; of which it is not fit in this Place to ſay more than this: Can we be ſo ſure that things are wrong ſetled, as we are that Chriſtians, of the ſame Communion eſpecially, ought to be at Peace, and live in Love, and concur in the ſtricteſt Union for their common Safety and Preſervation? We ned not be told how contrary it is to the Chriſtian Law, to act otherwiſe: But as for the Laws of the Land, it is not ſo evident that any thing is done contradictory to them; for Men of great Skill in thoſe Laws, affirm all things that have been acted, are conſiſtent with them. Why then ſhould we be violent in our Opinions, and Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about ſuch Matters; in which it becomes us to be more modeſt? Nay, why ſhould we give one another any trouble at all, about any thing whatſoever, when our Religion and our Intereſt require us to agree?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander Aphrodiſoens,</hi> as <hi>Maimonides</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>More Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voch. part. 1. c.</hi> 31.</note> hath obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, gives theſe three Reaſons, why Controverſies are
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:57178:20"/> multiplied, and cannot be determined. <hi>Firſt,</hi> The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty and depth of ſome things; in which, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, every body will be medling. <hi>Secondly,</hi> The weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Humane Underſtanding; of which no body will be ſenſible. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Love of Dominion and Victory, for which Men ſometimes contend more than for Truth. Their Reputation is ingaged, and they cannot yield, till they may come off with Credit. To which <hi>Maimonides</hi> himſelf adds a <hi>fourth;</hi> which is Cuſtom. We have a great love to that unto which we have been uſed; and are very loth to leave it. Which appears abundantly from what I have ſaid concerning the State of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in its beginning: Upon which let us reflect a little; for I will meddle with nothing elſe, in the Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>third</hi> thing I commended to your Study, the <hi>Knowledge of Times paſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>III. From whence we may learn, <hi>firſt,</hi> That Good Mens Prejudices may be ſuch, that they cannot be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently removed, though their Scruples be ungrounded. As we ſee by the Examples of the firſt and beſt Times, when ſome Chriſtians of the Jewiſh Nation could, by no means, be ſatisfied about ſuch things, as ſeem to us ſo plain, that we cannot but wonder they made a doubt about them. The generality of Chriſtians in the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile World eaſily underſtood, that they had no Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be Circumciſed, nor to abſtain from certain Meats and Drinks, and ſuch like things: and yet <hi>many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of the Jews who believed,</hi> as S. <hi>James</hi> tells S. <hi>Paul,</hi> (xxi. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.) were all ſo <hi>zealous of the Law,</hi> that they would not have endured him, if he had not charitably conſidered their weakneſs, and prudently ſweetned them by a temporary Compliance. What wonder then is it
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:57178:21"/> to ſee many diſſatisfied, in our preſent Circumſtances, about things, which give others no kind of ſcruple? Who ought to have no worſe thought of them, than this; that they labour under old Prejudices, as the Jewiſh Chriſtians did: which muſt be worn off by Time, but cannot be diſpoſſeſſed on a ſudden.</p>
               <p>2. For it is very obſervable, that moſt of the Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that troubled the Church in the beginning, ſprang from thoſe who had been bred up under a quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Perſuaſion, to that which was ſetled by the Authority of Chriſt and his Apoſtles. It was not the <hi>Gentiles</hi> that quarrelled with the <hi>Jews;</hi> but the <hi>Jews</hi> quarrelled with them, becauſe they would not look upon their Law, which had ſtood ſo many Ages, as of eternal Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And thus, we ſhould conſider, it will always be; ſtrong Prepoſſeſſions cannot eaſily be perſwaded to yield to the cleareſt Reaſons. Men will walk on in the way to which they have been accuſtomed; and hold faſt the Notions, which have been deeply riveted into their Minds. We ſee the Power, or Tyranny rather, of Cuſtom, in the very Habits and Faſhions of ſeveral Countries: unto which Men having been always uſed, they not only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thoſe of their own Country moſt decent; but are ſo in love with them, that they look upon all other as rude, nay as ridiculous. In ſhort, there is no greater Enemy to Knowledge, than this (as <hi>Maimonides</hi> notes in the Place before named); for as all Men are pleaſed with that to which they have been long habituated; ſo to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it may have become very profitable; and ſome may be afraid that their Authority will fall to the ground, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with that which they have long maintained.</p>
               <p>3. But notwithſtanding this, we learn from that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:57178:21"/> Example, we may be at peace; if we do as they did, or as they were taught to do. That is, be not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry one with another; but patiently bear with each others Infirmities; and <hi>be kindly affectioned one towards another in brotherly love,</hi> as if there were no Differences at all among us; and forbear raſh Judging on one ſide, and Contempt on the other: remembring we all ſerve the ſame Lord; and that it is neither for his Service nor his Honour, to have his Family divided; but agree to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in this, to do one another all the good they can, as the beſt Service they can do to him. Let our Heats at leaſt be abated, and not grow more violent than they have been formerly, (as they are in danger, I have ſhewn you, to be, when we reſiſt the Means of being made One) and then it is to be hoped, that we ſhall all come, in time, as the firſt Chriſtians did, to be <hi>perfectly joined together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgment.</hi> Which is the laſt thing I have to obſerve, from what hath been ſaid of the State of Things in the beginning.</p>
               <p>4. And we ſhall the ſooner come to it, if we will but live in love and peace together, notwithſtanding our preſent Differences. For this will make us capable of receiving and giving Satisfaction: which will not be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted from Enemies, or Strangers, or ſuch as are ſhy one of another. In order to which, let us forbear, as I ſaid, all cenſuring one of another; eſpecially all evil ſpeaking: Let us ſuppreſs Anger, and reſolve not to fall out, but to converſe one with another as Friends: and remember that the way to Agreement of all Parties, is not to bring Men to be of one Opinion, but to be of one Mind; which we may be, though of different Opinions: not by <hi>thinking the ſame things,</hi> but by <hi>thinking well one of</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:57178:22"/> endeavouring to preſerve Charity, as carefully as to preſerve Truth. For though Truth be great, yet Charity is greater: Which made a Man of no ſmall Learning and Piety ſay, (and, I think, not amiſs) <hi>Diſcord is ſo odious to me, that even Truth it ſelf diſpleaſes me, if</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eraſ. Epiſt. ad P. Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birium.</note> 
                  <hi>it be ſeditious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I intended to have preſſed one thing more upon you; which is, that you would not fail to ſtudy the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, in the late great and wonderful Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution: whereby he ſeems to me to have deſigned the ſame that he did to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they came out of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon;</hi> to <hi>give us all one heart, and one way, that we might fear him for ever; for the good of us, and of our children after us;</hi> as I obſerved before out of xxxii. <hi>Jer.</hi> 39. What a pity is it, that we ſhould loſe ſuch a bleſſed Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, of healing all our Breaches, and cloſing all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, with ſtrong Affection, in one firm Body, for our mutual Preſervation and Happineſs?</p>
               <p>But perhaps we may not agree in the Meaning of this Providence; and therefore I ſhall conclude with the Prayer of the Apoſtle, xiii. <hi>Heb.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now the God of Peace, which brought again from the dead our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that great Shepherd of the Sheep, through the Blood of the everlaſting Covenant, make you perfect in every good Work to do his Will, working in you that which is well-pleaſing in his ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt; To whom be Glory for ever and ever.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57178:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
